Guide to the Internationalist Books and Community Center Records, 1960-2011 RL.10170
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Internationalist Books and Community Center records
1960-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Internationalist Book Store (Chapel Hill, N.C.)
RL.10170
4.5 Linear Feet
The Internationalist Books and Community Center Records include materials documenting the organization and operation of the organization, particularly through its Board of Directors; lists of members and volunteers who staffed or supported the bookstore; advertisements and flyers, often handmade, created by store staff for events, sales, and other activities; Internationalist newsletters and drafts; zines and other printed materials collected and distributed by the bookstore; clippings and media coverage about Bob Sheldon and the organization; and other miscellaneous materials. Many of the materials documenting the activities of the Board of Directors were created and collected by Kelly Wooten, a Board member in the early 2000s.
Historical note
Internationalist Books and Community Center was founded by Bob Sheldon in 1981. Sheldon was a former UNC nurse who moved to Chapel Hill from Colorado in the 1970s. He was a community activist who vocally opposed the Gulf War. Sheldon was murdered in the store in 1991; the case remains unsolved, but many believe it was politically motivated.
Internationalist Books serves as a community space for discussion and dissemination of information about revolutionary and activist movements around the world, as well as alternative politics, economics, history, and lifestyles. The store began as a reading room on Henderson Street, in Chapel Hill, and later operated as an independent bookstore and community gathering place on Rosemary Street and Franklin Street in Chapel Hill. In 2000, Internationlist Books and Community Center achieved non-profit status, and began offering memberships. In 2014, the organization moved again to Lloyd Street in Carrboro.
Related Materials
The Rubenstein Library also holds the Bob Sheldon Papers, documenting his life and writings.
Provenance
The Internationalist Books and Community Center Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in May 2014.
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. 2 files of member and volunteer lists are closed to researchers for 25 years (until 2039) except by permission of the current manager of the Internationalist Bookstore.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Collection Overview
The Internationalist Books and Community Center Records include materials documenting the organization and operation of the organization, particularly through its Board of Directors; lists of members and volunteers who staffed or supported the bookstore; advertisements and flyers, often handmade, created by store staff for events, sales, and other activities; Internationalist newsletters and drafts; zines and other printed materials collected and distributed by the bookstore; clippings and media coverage about Bob Sheldon and the organization; and other miscellaneous materials. Many of the materials documenting the activities of the Board of Directors were created and collected by Kelly Wooten, a Board member in the early 2000s.
Booksellers and bookselling -- North Carolina -- Durham; Radicalism -- United States; Social change -- United States; Political activists -- Southern States; Independent bookstores -- North Carolina; Cooperative societies -- North Carolina; Zines -- United States -- Periodicals; Wooten, Kelly; Sheldon, Bob; Internationalist Books and Community Center; Internationalist Book Store (Chapel Hill, N.C.)
- Internationalist Books and Community Center records, 1960s-2000s; 1
  - Zine Library Binders, A-N, 1960s-2000s; 14 folders (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Zines, printed materials, and other bound volumes collected and distributed by the Internationalist Bookstore. The Zine Library at the Internationalist Bookstore included zines, serials, and monographs. These materials arrived at Rubenstein in binders, arranged alphabetically by title. That arrangement has been maintained in the archival collection. Topics covered by the Zine Library include anarchy, revolutionaries, communism, sexuality and gender, women's rights, poverty, race relations, African American history, and civil rights.
  - Zine Library Binders, O-Z, 1960s-2000s; 10 folders (Box 2)
  - The Realist, 1960-1970; 6 folders (Box 2)
    An incomplete run of The Realist magazine, published by the Realist Association. Issues included are 20, 27, 29, 32, 47, 48, 50, 55, 58, 61-67A, 70-72, 74-86B.
  - Press coverage and clippings, 1990s-2000s (Box 2)
    Clippings about Bob Sheldon's death and the events and activities of the Internationalist Bookstore.
  - Media Archive Binder, 1978-2006; 3 folders (Box 2)
    Articles and clippings about Bob Sheldon and the Internationalist Bookstore.
  - Flyers and Advertisements Binder: General Advertisements, undated (Box 3)
  - Flyers and Advertisements Binder: Volunteer Advertisements, undated (Box 3)
  - Flyers and Advertisements Binder: Event Advertisements, undated (Box 3)
  - Oversize Flyers and Advertisements: Event Advertisements (Oversize-box 60)
  - Newsletters: Article drafts, undated (Box 3)
    Article excerpts and drafts for the Internationalist newsletter.
  - Newsletters: Copies and proofs, 1992-2002 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters: Incomplete set, 1991-2006 (Box 3)
    Incomplete set of published Internationalist newsletters.
  - By-laws and guidelines, 1996-2000 (Box 3)
    Includes Internationalist Books and Community Center by-laws and a draft of personnel guidelines.
  - Non-profit corporation status documentation, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors meetings, 1999-2005 (Box 3)
    Meeting agendas, minutes, notes, and correspondence between Board members including documentation on Internationalist Bookstore finances, cash flow, management, and other topics. Notes kept by Kelly Wooten, Board of Directors co-chair and member.
  - Board of Directors retreats, 2002-2006; 3 folders (Box 3)
    Files kept by Kelly Wooten when planning and attending Board of Directors retreats in 2002, 2003, and 2006.
  - Board of Directors: Strategic Planning, 2001-2005; 3 folders (Box 3)
    Notes, research, and drafts from the Internationalist Books strategic planning sessions, held in 2002 and again in 2004-2005.
  - Store Environment Committee, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Inventory Committee, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Marketing/Outreach/Publicity Committees, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Direct mailings, undated (Box 3)
    Includes both drafts and examples of fundraising letters.
  - Bookstore resource lists, undated (Box 3)
    Pamphlets used by the bookstore with lists of notable children's or young adult books.
  - Bob Sheldon Award nominations, 2004-2005 (Box 3)
    Nominations and awards committee work for the Bob Sheldon Award in 2004 and 2005.
  - Carrboro Book Fairs, 2005-2006 (Box 3)
  - Event recaps, 2011 (Box 3)
    Event recaps kept by a store employee discussing attendance and participation at various events.
  - Membership database, undated (Box 3)
    Drafts from the creation of the membership database.
  - Member meetings, 2002-2005 (Box 3)
    Includes advertisements, correspondence, agendas, and meeting minutes from the Internationalist's annual member meetings.
  - Volunteer surveys, 2002-2006 (Box 3)
    Completed surveys and compiled survey results from Internationalist volunteers discussing their experiences in working at the bookstore.
  - Volunteer photographs, 2004 and undated (Box 3)
    A set of Polaroid photographs of bookstore volunteers.
  - Volunteer meetings, 2001-2006 (Box 3)
    Includes advertisements, correspondence, agendas, and meeting minutes from the Internationalist's recruitment, training, and use of community volunteers.
  - Membership lists, 2005 (Box 3)
    Access Restrictions
    This folder is closed to researchers for 25 years (until 2039), except with permission of the current Internationalist Books manager.
  - Volunteer lists, 2000-2004 (Box 3)
    This folder is closed to researchers for 25 years (until 2039), except with permission from the current Internationalist Books manager.